Guide to the Joseph Brodsky Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Writings, circa 1959-2000; Series II; 33.99; (86 boxes)
  - Prose
    - Individual prose writings
      - Essays
        - "Letter to a Senator," draft, 1989 (Box 84, Folder 2032)
        - "Literature and war -- A symposium," draft and printed version, 1985, 1998 (Box 84, Folder 2033)
        - "Litsa neobshchim vyrazhen'em" (Nobel lecture)
          - Russian language version, draft, 1987 (Box 85, Folder 2034)
          - Russian language version, drafts and printed version, 1987 (Box 86, Folder 2035-2037)
          - English translation by Barry Rubin, drafts and printed version, 1987 (Box 86, Folder 2038-2042)
        - "Looking back"
          See: "Pisatel' -- odinokii puteshestvennik"
        - "Making out in Moscow" (review of Moscow Farewell by George Feifer), draft and printed version, 1976 (Box 86, Folder 2043)
        - "The marriage of Cadmus and Harmony," drafts, 1993 (Box 86, Folder 2044)
        - "The meaning of meaning" (Review of The King of time: Selected writings of the Russian frutarian by Velimir Khlebnikov), draft and printed version, 1986 (Box 86, Folder 2045-2046)
        - "Men'she, chem edinitsa"
          See: "Less than one"
        - "The misquoted verse"
          See:"A commencement address"
        - "Muza placha"
          See: "The keening muse"
        - "Na storone Kavafisa"
          See: "Pendulum's Song"
        - "Nadezhda Mandelstam (1899-1980): An obituary"
          - English language version, draft and printed version, 1981 (Box 86, Folder 2047)
          - Russian translation by Aleksandr Batchan, printed version, 1981
          - Russian translation by A.Z. Kolotov, draft, 1988 (Box 86, Folder 2048)
          - Russian translation by Nina and Lev Losev, draft, undated (Box 86, Folder 2049)
          - French translation by Jean-Marc _____, draft, 1991 (Box 86, Folder 2050)
          - German translation by Marianne Frisch, printed version, 1982 (Box 86, Folder 2051)
          - German translation by Cynthia Dudejans Harris, draft, 1981 (Box 86, Folder 2052)
          - Swedish translation by unidentified translator, 1987 (Box 86, Folder 2053)
        - "Ninety years later"
          - English language version, drafts and printed version, 1994, undated (Box 86, Folder 2054-2060)
          - Russian translation by Aleksandr Sumerkin, draft, 1996 (Box 87, Folder 2061)
        - "O razume i svobode," draft, 1970s? (Box 87, Folder 2062)
        - "O Serezhe Dovlatove"
          - Russian language version, draft, undated (Box 87, Folder 2063)
          - English translation by Aleksandr Sumerkin, 1991, undated (Box 87, Folder 2064-2065)
        - "O tiranii"
          See: "On tyranny"
        - "Ob odnom stikhotvorenii"
          - Russian language version, proof and printed version, 1981 (Box 87, Folder 2066-2067)
          - English translation by Barry Rubin, draft and printed version, 1986, undated (Box 87, Folder 2068-2069)
        - "On Cavafy's side"
          See: "Pendulum's song"
        - "On Derek Walcott," draft and printed version, 1983 (Box 87, Folder 2070)
        - "On grief and reason," drafts, proof and printed version, 1990-1994 (Box 87, Folder 2071-2082)
        - "On money" (on Fedr Dostoevskii)
          - English language version, drafts, 1980 (Box 88, Folder 2083-2084)
          - Russian translation by A.Z. Kolotov, draft, 1988 (Box 88, Folder 2085)
        - "On Richard Wilbur"
          - Russian language version (untitled), draft, undated
          - English translation by Carl Proffer, draft and printed version, 1993 (Box 88, Folder 2086)
            See also: Series XI, Papers of Others -- Carl and Ellendea Proffer Papers -- Correspondence -- Unidentified
        - "On 'September 1st, 1939' by W.H. Auden"
          - Transcript of audio recording, undated (Box 88, Folder 2087-2089)
          - Draft, undated (Box 88, Folder 2090)
        - "On Sergei Dovlatov"
          See: "O Serezhe Dovlatove"
        - "On tyranny"
          - English language version, draft and printed version, 1979 (Box 88, Folder 2091-2093)
          - Russian translation by A.Z. Kolotov, draft, 1988 (Box 88, Folder 2094)
          - Russian translation by unidentified translator, draft, undated (Box 88, Folder 2095)
          - Russian translation by Arkadii Shufrin, printed version, 1990
          - Italian translation by unidentified translator, printed version, 1979 (Box 88, Folder 2096)
        - "Pendulum's song"
          - English language version, drafts and printed version, 1976-1977, undated (Box 88, Folder 2097-2098)
          - Russian translation by A. Losev, printed version, 1978 (Box 88, Folder 2099)
          - Russian translation by unidentified translator, draft, undated (Box 88, Folder 2100)
        - "Pisatel' -- odinokii puteshestvennik"
          - Russian language version, draft, 1972, undated (Box 88, Folder 2101)
          - English translation by Carl Proffer, draft and printed version, 1972 (Box 88, Folder 2102)
        - "Pis'mo Prezidentu"
          See: "Letter to a President"
        - "A place as good as any"
          - English language version, drafts and proof, 1991, undated (Box 88, Folder 2103-2105)
          - Russian translation by Elena Kasatkina, draft, 1996 (Box 88, Folder 2106)
        - "Playing games," draft and printed versions
          - English language version, draft and printed version, 1980 (Box 88, Folder 2107)
          - Italian translation by unidentified translator, printed version, 1980 (Box 88, Folder 2108)
        - "A poet and prose"
          See: "Poet i proza"
        - "Poet i proza," English translation by Barry Rubin, draft and printed version, undated (Box 88, Folder 2109-2112)
        - "The poet, the loved and and the Muse"
          See: "Altra ego"
        - "Poet's view: A true child of the century," printed version, 1980 (Box 88, Folder 2113)
        - "Poetry as a form of resistance to reality"
          See: "Poeziia kak forma soprotivleniia real'nosti"
        - "Poeziia kak forma soprotivleniia real'nosti"
          - Russian language version, draft and printed version, undated (Box 88, Folder 2114)
          - English language translation by Aleksandr Sumerkin and Jamey Gambrell, draft, proof and printed version, 1991-1997 (Box 88, Folder 2115-2116)
          - English language translation by Aleksandr Sumerkin and Jamey Gambrell, draft, proof and printed version, 1991-1997 (Box 89, Folder 2117)
        - "Poltory komnaty"
          See: "In a room and a half"
        - "Pokhvala skuke"
        - "Posle puteshestviia"
          - Russian language version, drafts, 1978?, undated (Box 89, Folder 2118-2119)
          - English translation by Aleksandr Sumerkin and Brodsky, drafts, 1978, undated (Box 89, Folder 2120-2124)
        - "The post-Communist nightmare: An exchange"
          See: "Letter to a president"
        - "Primechaniia k kommentariiu"
          - Russian language version, notes, drafts and printed version, 1992 (Box 89, Folder 2125-2128)
          - English translation by Jamey Gambrell and Alexander Sumerkin, notes, draft and printed version, 1999, undated (Box 89, Folder 2129-2131)
            Includes notes by Masha Vorobiov on English translations of poems by Marina Tsvetaeva and Boris Pasternak, which are discussed in the essay.
        - "The prison where I live," drafts, proof and printed version, 1995-1996 (Box 89, Folder 2132-2135)
        - "Profile of Clio," drafts and printed versions, 1991-1993 (Box 89, Folder 2136-2143)
        - "Puteshestvie v Stambul"
          - Russian language version, draft and printed version, 1985 (Box 90, Folder 2144-2145)
          - English translation by Alan Myers and Brodsky, drafts and printed version, 1985 (Box 90, Folder 2146-2149)
        - "Putevoditel' po pereimenovannomu gorodu"
        - "Razmyshlenie ob ischadii ada"
          - Russian language version, drafts, 1973 (Box 90, Folder 2150-2151)
          - English translation by Lena Karpov, drafts, proof and printed version, 1973 (Box 90, Folder 2152-2155)
        - "Rech' na stadione"
          See: "Speech at the stadium"
        - "A reflected city"
          See:"A guide to a renamed city"
        - "Reflections on a spawn of hell"
        - "Remembering her" (on Marie Angel), printed version, 1995
        - "Resisting the 'Machine'," (Review of Alexander Dolgun's story: An American in the Gulag, by Alexander Dolgun)
          - Russian language version (untitled), draft, 1975 (Box 90, Folder 2156)
          - English translation by Masha Vorobiov and Barry Rubin, drafts and printed version, 1975 (Box 90, Folder 2157-2159)
        - "The Russian Academy in Rome: Preliminary notes"
          - English language version, drafts, proofs and printed version, 1996 (Box 90, Folder 2160-2161)
          - Russian translation by Evgenii Shteiner, printed version, 1996 (Box 90, Folder 2162)
        - "S mirom derzhavnym ia byl lish' rebiacheski sviazan," printed version, undated (Box 90, Folder 2163)
        - "Se Gesù avesse letto la Quarta Egloga," printed version, 1981 (Box 90, Folder 2164)
        - "Some tips"
        - "Speech at the stadium"
          - English language version, drafts and printed version, 1988-1989 (Box 90, Folder 2165-2167)
          - Russian translation by Elena Kasatkina, draft, undated (Box 90, Folder 2168)
        - "Spoils of war"
          - English language version, drafts and printed versions, 1986-1996, undated (Box 90, Folder 2169-2173)
          - Russian translation by Aleksandr Sumerkin, drafts, undated (Box 91, Folder 2174-2175)
          - French translation by Véronique Schlitz, printed version, undated (Box 91, Folder 2176)
          - German translation by Jörg Trobitius, printed version, 1994 (Box 91, Folder 2177)
        - "Syn tsivilizatsii"
          See: "The child of civilization"
        - "The tenant's monologue"
          See: "Vzgliad s karuseli"
        - "To please a shadow"
          - English language version, draft, proof and printed version, 1983, undated (Box 91, Folder 2178-2180)
          - Russian translation by Elena Kasatkina, draft, undated (Box 91, Folder 2181)
          - Russian translation by unidentified translator, notes, undated (Box 91, Folder 2182)
            Questions from the translator; also includes questions about the translation of "Isaiah Berlin at Eighty" and Watermark.
        - "Translating Akhmatova" (Review of Poems of Akhmatova by Stanley Kunitz with Max Hayward)
          - Russian language version (untitled), draft, [1973]
          - English translation by Carl Proffer, draft, proof and printed version, 1973 (Box 91, Folder 2183)
        - "Trofeinoe"
          See: "Spoils of War"
        - "Trophies"
          See: "Spoils of war"
        - "V teni Dante"
        - "View from the merry-go-round"
        - "Virgil: Older than Christianity, a poet for the new age," printed version, 1981 (Box 91, Folder 2184)
        - "Vzgliad s karuseli"
          - Russian language version, printed version, 1990 (Box 91, Folder 2185)
          - English translation by Peter Scotto and Brodsky, drafts and printed version, 1990 (Box 91, Folder 2186-2189)
          - Ukranian translation by unidentified translator, printed version, 1990 (Box 91, Folder 2190)
        - "Warsaw uprising," draft, undated (Box 91, Folder 2191)
        - "A Western boyhood, in Russia"
        - "What the moon sees," draft and printed version, 1992 (Box 91, Folder 2192-2193)
        - "Why Milan Kundera is wrong about Dostoevsky," drafts and printed versions, 1985-1986 (Box 91, Folder 2194)
        - "Why Russian poets?" (on Bella Akhmadulina)
          - English language version, draft and printed version, 1977 (Box 91, Folder 2195)
          - Russian translation by Viktor Kulle, printed version, 1997 (Box 91, Folder 2196)
        - "Why the peace movement is wrong," printed version, 1984 (Box 91, Folder 2197)
        - "Wooing the inanimate," drafts, proofs and printed version, 1994-1995 (Box 91, Folder 2198-2201)
        - "Wooing the inanimate," drafts, proofs and printed version, 1994-1995 (Box 92, Folder 2202-2209)
        - "The writer in prison"
          See: "The prison where I live"
        - "Zametka dlia entsiklopedii" (on Vladimir Ufliand), drafts and printed version, 1989, undated (Box 92, Folder 2210)
        - "Zametka o Solov'eve," draft and printed version, 1971 (Box 92, Folder 2211)
        - Untitled prose writings
          - On orthography reform, draft, 1960s (Box 92, Folder 2212)
          - On Josif Stalin, drafts, 1978 (Box 92, Folder 2213-2214)
          - PEN Newsletter (on exile), draft, 1979 (Box 92, Folder 2215)
          - On teaching, draft, undated (Box 92, Folder 2216)
          - Autobiographical memoir, undated (Box 92, Folder 2217)
          - Foreword, on conscription and imprisonment, drafts, undated (Box 92, Folder 2218-2220)
          - On Ermanno Olmi's The tree of wooden clogs and Federico Fellini's Orchestra Rehearsal, draft, undated (Box 92, Folder 2221)
          - On Czesław Miłosz, draft, undated (Box 92, Folder 2222)
          - On I. F. Stone, draft, undated (Box 92, Folder 2223)
          - Review of "Chtoby rabotal poligon" by V. Reznik, draft, undated (Box 92, Folder 2224)
        - Unidentified fragments of essays, drafts (Box 93, Folder 2225-2236)
      - Introductions and afterwords to others' work
        - An Age Ago: a selection of nineteenth-century Russian poetry, foreword and biographical sketches, drafts, 1986 (Box 93, Folder 2237-2238)
        - Aleshkovskii, Iuz, introduction to Hand, 1989 (Box 93, Folder 2239)
        - Auden, W.H., introduction to an Italian anthology, undated (Box 93, Folder 2240)
        - Butler, Hubert, introduction to an unidentified volume of writings, 1994 (Box 93, Folder 2241-2242)
        - Cavafy, Constantine, introduction to poetry selected by Brodsky, drafts, proof and printed version, 1993 (Box 93, Folder 2243-2245)
        - Hardy, Thomas, table of contents and introduction to The Essential Hardy, draft and printed version, 1994-1995 (Box 93, Folder 2246-2249)
        - Herbert, Zbigniew
          - Introduction to an Italian edition, draft, 1992 (Box 93, Folder 2250)
          - Introduction to poetry selected by Brodsky, drafts and printed version, 1993 (Box 93, Folder 2251-2252)
        - Huchel, Peter, introduction to poetry selected by Brodsky, drafts and printed version, 1994 (Box 93, Folder 2253-2254)
        - Kees, Weldon, introduction to poetry selected by Brodsky, drafts and printed version, 1993 (Box 93, Folder 2255-2256)
        - Kiš, Danilo, introduction to A tomb for Boris Davidovich, draft and printed version, 1980? (Box 93, Folder 2257)
        - Kushner, Aleksandr, introduction to a volume of poetry
          - English language version, printed version, 1988, 1994 (Box 93, Folder 2258)
          - Russian translation [by Aleksandr Sumerkin?], draft, undated (Box 93, Folder 2259)
        - La Laguna de Venezia, introduction, drafts, 1995 (Box 94, Folder 2260-2261)
        - Mariangof, Anatolii, introduction to a French edition of The Cynics, draft, 1989 (Box 94, Folder 2262)
        - Miloslavskii, Iurii, introduction to Urban Romances & Other Stories, draft, undated (Box 94, Folder 2263)
        - Naiman, Anatolii, introduction to Remembering Akhmatova, drafts, 1991 (Box 94, Folder 2264)
        - Novikov, Denis, afterword to Okno v Ianvare, draft, undated (Box 94, Folder 2265)
        - Platonov, Andrei, foreword to Collected Works
          - Russian language version, draft, proof and printed version, 1978 (Box 94, Folder 2266)
          - English translation by Carl Proffer, proof, 1978 (Box 94, Folder 2267)
        - Proffer, Carl, ed., foreword to Modern Russian Poets on Poetry
          - Russian language version, draft, 1976 (Box 94, Folder 2268)
          - English translation by Carl Proffer, draft, 1976 (Box 94, Folder 2269)
        - Propertius, Sextus, introduction to poetry selected by Brodsky, drafts and printed version, 1993 (Box 94, Folder 2270-2272)
        - Rein, Evgenii, introduction to Protiv chasovoi strelki
          - Russian language version, draft and printed version, 1991 (Box 94, Folder 2273)
          - English translation by Jamey Gambrell, drafts, 1994 (Box 94, Folder 2274)
        - Tchernichova, Elena, introduction to a book, draft, 1991 (Box 94, Folder 2275)
        - Walcott, Derek, introduction to a Swedish-language volume of poetry, drafts, 1991 (Box 94, Folder 2276-2278)
      - Letters to Editors
        - Unidentified publications, 1960s (Box 94, Folder 2279)
        - Literator (on literacy), printed version, 1967 (Box 94, Folder 2280)
        - American Poetry Review (on Denise Levertov), drafts and printed version, 1973 (Box 94, Folder 2281)
        - Novoe Russkoe Slovo (on M. Shtiker), draft, 1973 (Box 94, Folder 2282)
        - New York Review of Books (on Vladimir Maramzin), draft and printed version, 1974 (Box 94, Folder 2283)
        - New York Review of Books (on Tomas Venclova), draft and printed version, 1976 (Box 94, Folder 2284)
        - New York Review of Books (on Konstantin Azadovskii), printed version, 1981 (Box 94, Folder 2285)
        - Windsor Star (on Margaret Atwood), draft, 1982 (Box 94, Folder 2286)
        - Unidentified publication (on Solidarity), draft, 1982 (Box 94, Folder 2287)
        - New York Times (on the death of Aleksandr Brodskii), printed version, 1984 (Box 94, Folder 2288)
        - Harper's (on the peace movement), printed version, 1985 (Box 94, Folder 2289)
        - Times Literary Supplement (on Stephen Spender), printed version, 1985 (Box 94, Folder 2290)
        - [ Times Literary Supplement ?] (on Donald Davie), draft, 1988 (Box 94, Folder 2291)
        - International Herald Tribune (on Leon Wieseltier), draft, 1989 (Box 94, Folder 2292)
        - Novoe Russkoe Slovo (on the "Aprel'" Committee), 1989 (Box 94, Folder 2293)
        - Moskovskie Novosti (on Ellendea Proffer), draft, 1990 (Box 94, Folder 2294)
        - Times Literary Supplement (on Salman Rushdie), drafts and printed version, 1991 (Box 94, Folder 2295)
        - New York Times (on Guggenheim Museum exhibit of Russian art), drafts, 1992 (Box 94, Folder 2296)
        - Unidentified publication (on Vladimir Meilakh), undated (Box 94, Folder 2297)
      - Short Fiction
        - "Shooting an Elephant" by George Orwell, Russian translation by Brodsky, draft, undated (Box 94, Folder 2298)
        - "Vspakhannoe pole," short story, draft, 1961 (Box 94, Folder 2299)
  - Dramatic Writing
    Dramatic Writing includes typescript drafts, proofs and printed versions of original plays by Brodsky and his translations of other's plays, spanning the years 1984-1990.
    - Democracy
      See: Demokratiia
    - Demokratiia
      - Russian language version
        - Act I, drafts and printed version, undated (Box 95, Folder 2300-2303)
        - Act II, drafts, 1992 (Box 95, Folder 2304-2306)
      - English translation by Brodsky
        - Act I, drafts and proof, 1989 (Box 95, Folder 2307-2310)
        - Act II, drafts and proof, 1996, undated (Box 95, Folder 2311-2316)
          Also available through Access Services: Disk#03.
      - Italian translation by unidentified translator, printed version, 1990
    - Derevo, draft, undated (Box 95, Folder 2317)
    - E-777, by Brendan Behan, Russian translation by Brodsky, notes and drafts, 1990, undated (Box 95, Folder 2318-2320)
    - Koroleva Kremlia ili Stalin v Gollivude, by Iuz Aleskovskii and Joseph Brodsky
      - Russian version, draft, 1989 (Box 96, Folder 2321)
      - English translation by unidentified translator, 1989 (Box 96, Folder 2322)
    - The man with six toes on his right foot
      See: Koroleva Kremlia ili Stalin v Gollivude
    - Marbles
      See: Mramor
    - Mramor
      - Russian language version, proofs and printed version, 1984, undated (Box 96, Folder 2323-2326)
      - English translation by Alan Myers and Brodsky, draft, proofs and printed versions, 1985-1989, undated (Box 96, Folder 2327-2335)
    - Rim (alternate title for Mramor ), draft, undated (Box 97, Folder 2336)
    - Rosencrantz and Guildenstern are Dead, by Tom Stoppard, Russian translation by Brodsky, draft, undated (Box 97, Folder 2337)
    - The Steel Man, proposal for a documentary film on Joseph Stalin, draft, undated (Box 97, Folder 2338)
  - Collected Works
    Collected Works consists of a multi-volume samizdat collection and a multi-volume printed series that collect several genres of Brodsky's writing. The samizdat collection compiled by Vladimir Maramzin contains the most complete documentation of Brodsky's pre-emigration writings. The material from Sochineniia Iosifa Brodskogo (primarily consisting of proofs) is fragmentary but includes some material that does not appear in the final printed volumes.
    - Sobranie sochinenii, compiled by Vladimir Maramzin
      - Volume 1 (Poetry, 1957-63), typescript and photocopy, 1973 (Box 98, Folder 2339-2346)
      - Volume 2 (Poetry, 1964-1967), typescript and photocopy, 1973 (Box 99, Folder 2347-2351)
      - Volume 3 (Poetry, 1968-1972), typescript and photocopy, 1973 (Box 99, Folder 2352-2355)
      - Volume 4 (Children's poems, occasionals, prose and other works), photocopy, 1973, 1977 (Box 100, Folder 2356-2357)
    - Sochineniia Iosifa Brodskogo, edited by Iakov Gordin
      - Volume 2, printed version, 1992 (Box 101, Folder 2358)
        Corrected by Brodsky.
      - Volume 4, proof, [1998] (Box 101, Folder 2359)
      - Volume 5, proofs, [1999] (Box 101, Folder 2360-2364)
      - Volume 6, copies of essays and proofs, [2000] (Box 101, Folder 2365)
      - Volume 6, copies of essays and proofs, [2000] (Box 102, Folder 2369)
      - Volume 7, proofs, [2001] (Box 102, Folder 2370-2371)
      - Unidentified volumes, proofs, undated (Box 102, Folder 2372-2373)
  - Writings of Others
    Writings of Others consists of holograph and typescript drafts of writings that the authors sent or gave to Brodsky. Many of these writings were sent by fans seeking Brodsky's opinion on their manuscripts; others were sent by former students and friends. The manuscripts contain chiefly poetry, but also include some essays, novels and dramatic works.
    Photocopies of printed writings are filed in Series IX, Printed Material.
    Arranged alphabetically by author. Poems dedicated to Brodsky are filed together at the end of the listing.
    - A_____, I_____, Poems, 1990-1991 (Box 103, Folder 2374)
    - Abaeva-Mairs, Diana, Interview with Isaiah Berlin about Brodsky, undated (Box 103, Folder 2375)
    - Adamovskii, Iurii, Poems, undated (Box 103, Folder 2376)
    - Akhmatova, Anna, English translations by various translators, undated (Box 103, Folder 2377)
    - Aleinik, Aleksandr, Poems, 1995 (Box 103, Folder 2378)
    - Aleshkovskii, Iuz, "Zagranichnaia igrushka", undated (Box 103, Folder 2379)
    - Allison, Alla, The Golden Age, 1989 (Box 103, Folder 2380)
    - Aly-Arossov, Il'ia, Poems, undated (Box 103, Folder 2381)
    - Andreev, Aleksandr, Stikhi 1988-1991, circa 1991 (Box 103, Folder 2382)
    - Andronov, Aleksandr, Poems, 1993 (Box 103, Folder 2383)
    - Anton, John P., The poetry and poetics of Constantine P. Cavafy, undated (Box 103, Folder 2384)
    - Arolovich, Ella, Vanya's adventures around the world, 1993 (Box 103, Folder 2385-2386)
    - Attardi, Luigi, Poems, 1987 (Box 103, Folder 2387)
    - Auden, W. H., "An odd ball" (on Chaadayev), circa 1973 (Box 103, Folder 2388)
    - Azadovskii, K.M et alia, Collection of memoirs about Brodsky, 1988 (Box 103, Folder 2389)
      Authors include Viktoriia Belominskaia, N.I. Grudinina, Leonid Menaker, Tat'iana Nikol'skaia, B. I. Tishchenko and Vladimir Ufliand.
    - Bäckström, Claes, Poems, undated (Box 103, Folder 2390)
    - Barry, Celia, Poems, undated (Box 103, Folder 2391)